Today's דף daf, *daf* is, or our דף *daf* is ס"ה *Samech
Hei*, and we pick up at the two dots. תנו רבנן *Tanu
Rabbanan*. So we're dealing again with this woman who's married to a
man for 10 years, can't have kids, so divorced, but with an
interesting split. On the one hand, an assumption that it is not
her fault so that she can go ahead and marry another man
who still needs, who's still, the husband hasn't had kids, but on
the other hand an assumption that might, she might be a factor
that he's told to go ahead and marry another woman. So now
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* and then we dealt with חזקה chazaka *Chazakah*
after two or three times. Certainly by the third time, well that's
the debate of רבי *Rebbe* and רבן שמעון בן גמליאל *Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel* after how many times would it be established that it's
because of her that she, that's where the infertility problem lies. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this: תנו רבנן *Tanu Rabbanan*, four
lines from the top on ס"ה עמוד א' *Samech Hei Amud Aleph*.
ניסת לראשון ולא היו לה בנים ושני ולא היו לה בנים *Nisset
lirishon vilo hayu lah banim vishaini vilo hayu lah banim*, so she
married to the first one no kids, second one no kids, so
that's twice, so that should be the debate of רבי *Rebbe* and
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל *Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel* at this stage. ושלישי
לא lo. תינשא אלא למי שיש לו בנים *Vishlishi lo tinasei ela
lemi sheyeish lo banim*, don't marry a third person following רבי *Rebbe*
who says that after two times either it's a חזקה chazaka *Chazakah*
or at least we have to be concerned. So it seems like
it's really a good reason to assume it is the problem lies
with her. So don't marry a third man unless the person has
already fulfilled the מצוה mitzvah *Mitzvah*, the man has already fulfilled the
מצוה mitzvah פרו ורבו Pru U'rvu. *Mitzvah Peru uRevu*. אלא למי שיש
לו בנים *Ela lemi sheyeish lo banim*. ניסת למי שאין לו בנים
תצא בלא כתובה ktuba, *Nisset lemi she'ein lo banim taitzei belo kesubah*.
If she marries somebody who does not have kids, then she has
to get, then she's divorced without a כתובה ktuba *kesubah* because then
it has been established that it's the problem lies with her. And
this guy needs to have kids. Of course the question is why
not marry another wife without divorcing her, we'll get to that in
a minute, but anyway, but since that, but then she gets divorced
without a כתובה ktuba. *kesubah* because then he has to get, have
more kids, and the problem is identified as lying with her. איבעיא
להו *Iba'ya lehu*, now they ask the question: ניסת לשלישי ולא היו
בנים מהו דליתבעו הנך קמאי *Nisset lishlishi vilo hayu banim mahu delitve'u
hanach kamaei*? So let's say she goes ahead and she marries the
third guy and she waits, and she waits for
three, and she waits, you know, 10 years and still doesn't have
kids with the third guy. So the first two guys paid her
כתובה ktuba, *kesubah* because the point was it might not have been
identified as necessarily her problem, right? So that's why that split, pay
the כתובה ktuba. *kesubah* but these guys get remarried, it's not exactly
clear where the problem lies, but it's not clear that it's her
problem and so on. So now she's with three guys and she
still hasn't had kids. So now it's firmly been established that it's
her problem. Can the first two guys go back to her and
say, give us back the כתובה ktuba. *kesubah* money? It's clearly been
proven that it was because of you. מהו דליתבעו הנך קמאי, מי
מצו אמרו לה *Mahu delitve'u hanach kamaei, mi matzu amru lah*? Can
they say to her, איגלאי מילתא דאת הוא דגרמת *Iglai miltza de'at
hu digramat*? It's been revealed that you are the cause. או דילמא
מצי אמרה להו *O dilma matzi amrah lehu*? Or she can say
back to them, השתא הוא דאכחש *Hashta hu de'achash*? Now my body
has gotten weaker, meaning, you know, maybe I was only a partial
cause, who knows? Maybe I wasn't a cause at all, but the
other, there's been time has passed. It's been 20 years since I've
been married to you the first guy and 10 years the second
guy. So maybe now it's a new problem or it's more severe.
מסתברא מצי אמרה להו השתא הוא דאכחש *Mistavra matzi amrah lehu hashta
hu de'achash*. Yes, she can say that to them, that it might
be now that the problem has gotten worse and the basic principle
being, again, the interesting question is like who has the burden of
proof? Throughout all of this it really sounds like she's entitled to
her כתובה kesuva. *kesubah* and they have the burden of proof. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this: מסתברא *Mistavra*... Okay, so
איבעיא להו *Iba'ya lehu*, so ask the question: ניסת לרביעי והיו לה
בנים *Nisset lirvei'i vehayu lah banim*, she gets married to a fourth
guy and now she has kids. So מהו דתיתבעי לשלישי *Mahu detitvei
lishlishi*? Can she go back to the third guy, because remember the
third guy already wasn't paying her the כתובה kesuva. *kesubah*, right? Because
by the third guy we already said she shouldn't marry him. There's
enough of a basis, at least according to רבי *Rebbe*, to say
don't marry the third guy, so even though it's not a hundred
percent proof, there's enough of a basis that therefore the, that
guy number three shouldn't marry her and if he does marry her
doesn't pay a כתובה kesuva. *kesubah*. But now she marries a fourth
guy and has kids.
Can she go back to the third guy and demand her כתובה
kesuva. *kesubah*? מהו דתיתבעי לשלישי *Mahu detitvei lishlishi*? אמרינן
לה *Amrinan lah*, so we say to her, שתיקותייך יפה מדיבורייך *Shtikosayich
yafah midibura'yich*. Your silence is better than your speech. Why? דמצי אמר
לה Amar lah, *De'matzi amar lah*, because if you go back to
guy three and say, give me my כתובה kesuva. *kesubah* money, it's
now clear that I'm able to have kids, דמצי אמר לה Amar
lah, *De'matzi amar lah*, he can say to her, אנא אדעתא דהכי
לא גירשתיך *Ana ada'ata de'hachi lo garashtich*. Oh, you're fertile? Had I
known that, I never would have divorced you, says guy number three.
And therefore the גט get. *get* is not good, it was a
טעות *to'us*, and therefore you're still my wife, and therefore your kid
is a ממזר mamzer, *mamzer*. ממזר mamzer? with this next guy. So
if she don't press her suit that, "Hey look, I was always
fertile, it shows that it was really your problem," or whatever he
might she might be saying, because then that'll raise questions in terms
of the divorce from the third guy. So the גמרא Gemara says
one minute, if that's a legitimate concern then who cares whether she
says it or not?
מתקיף לה רב פפא, Matkif la Rav Pappa, רב פפא Rav Pappa
asks on this, "אי אישתקא אישתקין? ee ishtaka ishtakin? And how can
we be quiet? אנן מי שתקינן? anan mi shatkinan? נמצא גט בטל
ובנים ממזרים." nimtza get batel u-vanim mamzerim. If that's a legitimate concern
that now it seems that she really is fertile, then we should
raise the problem that maybe retroactively it was a bad גט. get,
So the גמרא Gemara says, "אלא אמרינן השתא הוא דאבריא." ella amrinan
hashta hu d'avraya. You're right. You know what, we're not going to
raise that claim, partly because as you might remember in earlier גמרא
Gemara, about similar issues, basically he just has to divorce her accepting
that the facts are what they are, you know, regardless of how
things reveal themselves later on, and we're not going to say that
because of what happens later that's going to make it, A, indicate
what the facts were retroactively and B, even if they do indicate
what the facts were retroactively, that it's not going to be relevant
because the divorce was based on his knowledge at the time. But
nevertheless, she is not in a position to go ahead and press
her claim retroactively because we'll say that her situation now has improved,
and now something has happened different than what it was before. So
the basic point is that we don't retroactively revisit. And that's really
like in everybody's best interest. Okay? So if we would retroactive- so
A, the general rule is that she has the presumption, the burden
of proof is on him not to pay the כתובה, kesuva. but
when in the case of the third marriage he didn't pay the
כתובה kesuva. because the evidence had been that she- there's a very
good chance that she was infertile and was after two times and
so on, we're not going to go ahead and afterwards revisit that,
any later evidence we'll assume was a change of status but we'll
judge the case as the way it was judged at the time.
So Philip you had a question.
Philip, so you:
"But does this mean for example in business or damages context that
we might revisit claims if there isn't a counter assumption that can
be articulated?"
That's a pretty broad question, I'm not sure, but the basic point
is that there are all these issues about דברים שבלב אינם דברים
dvarim she-balev einam dvarim and what were the presumptions at the time
and we don't- you know we're not going to regularly revise things
based on things that only get revealed later. Yeah, yeah.
"Is there by that first opinion nothing could might ever be finished
in any..."
Right, so that's basically the point that normally we always do it
based on the best assumptions at the time. Right. Okay, okay. הוא
אמר מינה. Hu amar minei. Now, he says- let's get to a
classic case, I mean one would imagine what we're about to read
is the standard scenario. He says the reason we're not having kids
is her problem, והיא אמרה מיניה, v'hi amra mineh, and she says
it's his problem. Now presumably that's normally the case and the הלכה
halacha is you know divorce her but you give a כתובה. kesuva,
So there are whole major questions in תוספות Tosafos like what are
the exact circumstances here that presumably not what we've been talking about
until now? But anyway let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. אמר
רבי אמי, Amar Rabi Ami, דברים שבינו לבינה נאמנת. d'varim she-beino l'veina
ne'emenes.
Things that relate to the things that are between the two of
them, she's believed. Now what does that mean? I mean she's believed.
How does she know where the source of the infertility is? So
let's keep on- let's read a little bit more and then we'll
see if we say something about this. במאי טעמא? B'mai ta'ama? And
why is that reason? היא קים לה ביורה כחץ הוא לא קים
ליה ביורה כחץ. Hi kama leh b'yora k'chetz, hu lo kama leh
b'yora k'chetz. So the גמרא Gemara identifies that there's a specific problem
here that is the cause, which is that he is not able
to have a strong ejaculation. The language is יורה כחץ, yora k'chetz,
does he shoot like an arrow, okay, so that- does it come
out like in a strong stream? So if she's saying that that's
the problem, we say she's in a better position to be aware
of that than he is during the act of sex. So
and somehow therefore we believe her. Of course the question is who
says that that's the only problem? And why do we need that
to be the specific claim? Do we- I mean we already said
in general that since it might be his problem, right, he pays
her the כתובה, kesuva, it might be לא זכה להיבנות ממנה. lo
zachah l'hibanos mimenah. But anyway let's read a little bit more and
then we'll see if we can sort of unpack this a little
bit.
אמר איהו איזיל אינסיב איתתא ואיבדוק נפשאי. Amar ihu, eizal insiv itata
v'ivdok nafshai. So he says, "Okay, I'll tell you what, I'm going
to go ahead and marry another woman and let's see if I
have kids with her. And if I have kids with her then
it'll prove that it's your problem and I don't have to pay
you your
כתובה." kesuva אמר רבי אמי בזו יוציא ויתן כתובה. Amar Rabi Ami,
be-zo yotzi ve-yitein ketubah. If he wants to say that, then he
doesn't have the option of doing that. Before he marries another woman,
he has to divorce her and give her the כתובה.
Kesuvah Right, שאני אמר shani amar
now again it's funny that the way it's framing it here as
I said in the context of let me try to prove where
the problem is, why doesn't it just say let's say he doesn't
want to divorce her and let's say he just wants to marry
another woman to have kids, whoever- wherever the problem is? But presumably
if that's what he wants to do nobody's going to stop him.
But here he's doing it as a way of- anyway let's see,
he says if that's what he wants to do... Presumably if that's
what he wants to do nobody's going to stop him but here
he's doing it as a way of anyway so let's see. He
says if that's what you want to do then go ahead and
then you gotta divorce and give a כתובה. Kesuvah Why? שאני אומר
כל הנושא אשה על אשתו יוציא ויתן כתובה. She'ani omer kol hanosei
isha al ishto yotzi veyiten kesuva. Anybody who marries another wife on
his
after his first wife, presumably if the first wife protests. That the
first wife is able to actually say, I do not want you
to marry a second wife and if you do, then you have
to give me a כתובה. Kesuvah And,
right, exactly. So this is getting interesting, even though this is a
very important גמרא, Gemara because even though we know הלכה halacha about
polygamy, the question is, was it considered to be an acceptable norm
in society or not? And the first opinion here is like, I
don't care whether technically it's הלכתית halachically allowed, it's considered, you know,
a violation of the first wife's rights, and if you want to
do that then you have to, and she protests, you have to
divorce her and give her her כתובה. Kesuvah רבא Rava אמר amar
נושא אדם כמה נשים על אשתו והוא דאית ליה למיזן נינהו. nosei
adam kama nashim al ishto vehu d'is lei l'mizan ninhu. No,
a person's entitled, a man's entitled to marry many women even after
his first wife as long as he has the ability to support
them. Okay, so this little debate in this גמרא Gemara is a
major question about how much do we tolerate polygamy or not, or
how much do we see it as fundamentally not acceptable? Right? And
this is as I've mentioned to you before, winds up being basically
a debate between the בבלי Bavli and the ירושלמי Yerushalmi and ספרד
Sefard and אשכנז, Ashkenaz, and has a lot to do with whether
they were living in a polygamous or monogamous culture. But the reality
is that even in polygamous cultures, you would never actually have a
man married to many women unless he actually was wealthy and could
support many wives. So that's basically what רבא Rava is saying. Yes.
What about the עגונה aguna situation? Does it apply, or does it
not apply? The first opinion?
What do you mean?
That in other words, can a wife say the man has to
divorce and the...
Yeah, I mean, in a lot of cases we have that a
woman...
right. Yeah, I mean, but you know, yeah, I mean, the problem
with עגונה aguna is that you have obviously even more, yes, I
mean,
you know, if a man is actually going ahead and marrying another
woman while he hasn't given his first wife a גט, Get, but
often there's other many reasons to say that he has to divorce
and give her her כתובה. Ketubah. The problem is whether בית דין
Beis Din is prepared to actually do, you know, compel it or
not. It's not as to what הלכה halacha sort of says what
happens.
Okay. What about רבי אמי Rabbi Ami from ארץ ישראל?
Eretz Yisrael? That is a good question. I don't know, but that
would track nicely. Somebody can check. Okay. הוא אמר אפלתה בגו עשר
והיא אמרה לא אפליטי. Hu amar apalta b'go eser ve'hi amra lo
apaliti. He said, you had a miscarriage during the ten years, so
therefore I don't have to divorce you yet. And she said, I
didn't have a miscarriage and therefore I demand my divorce and I
demand my כתובה. Ketubah. Okay,
which is again funny, which is a case where basically she wants
to divorce and he doesn't.
Okay, so the הלכה halacha is, because maybe she wants the opportunity
to get remarried and have more kids. אמר רבי אמי אף בזו
היא נאמנת. Amar Rabbi Ami af b'zu hi ne'emenes. She's believed here
too.
The same way she was believed in terms of the question of
where the source of the infertility lies, here she's also believed, and
she can basically... and therefore he would say he has to divorce
her and give her the כתובה. Ketubah דאי איתא דהפילה נפשה באקרתא
לא מחזקה. D'ei issa d'hapila nafsha b'akarta lo machzaka. Because if it
were... because
he's basically saying you haven't been yet established to be the source
of the problem, to have ten years without a child. And she
is saying,
right, because there was a miscarriage. And she is saying no, it's
been ten years, I haven't had a child, and therefore you need
to divorce me and give the כתובה. Ketubah So רבי אמי Rabbi
Ami is saying she wouldn't have made that up because she wouldn't
have claimed if it were not true, she wouldn't have claimed that
I've gone ten years without having a kid and without even having
a miscarriage, you know, because that basically establishes her as infertile. Now,
of course we said הלכתית halachically it's not proven she's infertile, she
could marry another man, but nevertheless, that's, you know, it's presumed... like
there's clearly a concern here. What? It's not good for a שידוך.
shidduch. It's not good for a שידוך, shidduch, exactly. So she wouldn't
have been saying this if it were not true even though in
the immediate context it allows her to demand a divorce and get
a כתובה, Ketubah we will believe her.
רבי אמי Rabbi Ami was in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael.
Was in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Oh, good. So that really does
track. So רבי אמי Rabbi Ami therefore saying that he can't have
two wives and רבא Rava saying he can have two wives exactly
tracks ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and בבל. Bavel. Very good.
Okay, so,
okay, now. הפילה וחזרה והפילה וחזרה והפילה. Hapila v'chazra v'hapila v'chazra v'hapila.
So let's say she had three miscarriages. So now she doesn't have
a חזקה chazaka of not being able to conceive, but maybe she
has a חזקה of not being able to carry to term. So
the גמרא Gemara says הוחזקה לנפלים. huchzaka l'nefalim. So she does have
a חזקה of miscarrying, and that would presumably mean that if you
look at רש"י, Rashi, יוציא ויתן כתובה שמא לא זכה ליבנות ממנה.
yotzi v'yiten kesuva shema lo zachah libanos mimena. So even without ten
years, you know, he divorces her although רש"י, Rashi, but he gives
the כתובה, ketubah which is again interesting, they're walking this line, לא
זכה ליבנות ממנה. lo zachah libanos mimena. It's still not proven that
it's only her problem. It might be the combination of the problem,
so she still gets her כתובה and she could still marry somebody
else. הוא אמר הפילה תרי והיא אמרה תלת. Hu amar hapila terei
ve'hi amra telasa. Now he said you miscarried twice and I don't
yet have to divorce you and give you a כתובה and she
said no it's been three times. אמר רבי יוחנן בר אלעזר עובדא
הוה בבי מדרשא Amar Rabbi Yochanan bar Elazar uvda hava be bei
midrasha this happened in the בית מדרש Beis Medrash I mean I
assume the debate occurred in the בית מדרש Beis Medrash דאמרו היא
מהימנא de-amru hi mehemana she's believed דאי איתא דלא
אפלה נפשה בנפילי לא מחזקה d'ee itta d'lo aplah nafshah benefili lo
machzeka because same reason she's believed because if it weren't true even
though it's allowing her to win her claim right now and to
get the divorce with the כתובה but she would not go ahead
and say something that would establish her as a woman who regularly
miscarries. So again interestingly we believe her even though you know even
though she has a vested interest in this particular case because it's
a type of a מיגו migo and other types of comments we
have statements we have other times that people would not make these
claims if they were false. So again what's quite fascinating here is
the whole series of cases where she's essentially the one suing for
divorce presumably A she wants her כתובה and B maybe she wants
an opportunity to get remarried. Okay and in all these debates we
basically believe her over him. What is a quite interesting question is
how is this actually different than some of the earlier cases in
the משנה Mishnah itself where anyway it was the case where we
believed him? What sort of special particularly about the initial issue of
the יורה כחץ? yoreh k'chetz? So let me just quickly quickly check
תוספות. Tosfos. Okay
no so he has a couple of complicated answers I don't want
to get into it. But anyway so without getting into it at
least we see the basic sort of thrust here about this and
as I was saying it's very it's quite fascinating in terms of
what just comes brought up as an aside but about the husband's
entitlement to marry a second wife and whether he really is entitled
or whether you know he has to go ahead and give a
כתובה which is really the polygamy-monogamy debate. Yes.
Yeah you mentioned it briefly. Do you think that לא זכה להבנות
ממנה lo zachah libanos mimena has any theological implication to it?
Yeah because the גמרא Gemara says before you know we... Yeah exactly
so the גמרא Gemara seems to very much be learning this and
yeah exactly. All right so let's move on to the next משנה
Mishnah which wraps up the immediate discussions of פרו ורבו. Pru U'rvu
האיש מצווה על פרו ורבו אבל לא האשה. Haish metzuveh al pru
u'rvu aval lo haisha.
The man is commanded on פרו ורבו Pru U'rvu and not the
woman which is quite fascinating. רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא אומר על שניהם
הוא אומר Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka omer al shneihem hu omer no
for both of them God says ויברך אתם אלהים ויאמר להם אלהים
פרו ורבו Vayivarech osam Elokim vayomer lahem Elokim pru u'rvu
which is a pretty reasonable argument besides the fact that the woman
is the one having the babies. Okay so let's take a look.
מנא הני מילי? Minani milei? Where's this from? אמר רב אילעא משום
רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון אמר קרא Amar Rav Illa mishum Rabbi Elazar
b'rei d'Rabbi Shimon amar kra the verse says ומלאו את הארץ וכבשה.
u'milu es ha'aretz v'chivshuha. So where do the Rabbis get the idea
that it's only the man's מצווה? mitzvah?
Because the end of the verse says fill the land and conquer
it. איש דרכו לכבוש ואין אשה דרכה לכבוש. Ish darko lichvosh v'ein
isha darkah lichvosh. So it's the man that is conquers the land
and not the woman so therefore presumably even though it says that
God said to them it really means God said to the man
because clearly the end of the verse refers to the man.
But we have an echo from מגילת אסתר... Megillas Esther... Well we're...
we'll get to that in a minute. אדרבה וכבשה תרתי משמע! Adderaba
v'chivshuha tarti mashma!
What are you talking about? It says in the plural וכבשה v'chivshuha
אתם תכבשו אותה Atem tichvishu osa
right? You conquer the land you plural. So what do you mean
it's talking only to the man? אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק וכבשה
כתיב. Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak v'chivshah ksiv. No because it's written
without the ואו. vav. Okay which is pretty funny that you take
a פסוק pasuk which clearly it's talking to both of them and
based on a קרי וכתיב kri u'chsiv here you basically have it
talking only to the man. So the question is also like what's
theologically behind this idea or what's religiously behind this idea? So some
want to say that based on like the גמרא Gemara we saw
before where the גמרא Gemara says like לשבת lasheves you know that
part of the idea of פרו ורבו Pru U'rvu is not just
populating the world but settling the world and you might remember that
idea before so that might be seen here that it's sort of
seen that if the מצווה mitzvah is to settle the world so
maybe that's primarily the man's responsibility. The man is the one that
goes out right and right the hunter-gatherer debate split or whatever you
know the man's going out and I don't know building society and
the woman's staying at home and therefore if that's the idea of
the man settling the world so also the idea of populating which
is part of this idea of לשבת. lasheves. That's one idea which
probably is a simple I would say in the context of these
פסוקים psukim and not the simplest in terms of how we want
to think about פרו ורבו pru u'rvu but the simplest in context
of how the גמרא's Gemara reading this. Another thing which is very
which is like very suggestive here is what Rabbi Dov was saying
which is I'm trying to remember who the first one to say
this is but a number of אחרונים achronim want to say that
it is a וכבשה v'chivshah now refers not to you the man
conquer the earth but you the man you know conquer the woman
and that basically this is linked to the idea
that the גמרא Gemara sees you know the גמרא Gemara that talks
about woman as קרקע עולם karka olam in terms of the act
of forced sex and so on and sees the man as sort
of the initiator and more of the actor in the act of
sex and the woman as more passive and therefore would understand that
the reason the given to the man is if you see the
man as the initiator and active one and the woman as the
passive one and you know having kids comes through having sex so
then the man becomes the one that is commanded. So that's how
someone wants to sort of read into these פסוקים psukim here although
again not exactly what the גמרא Gemara is saying but you know
on the other hand not that far you know you can sort
of see how it could be very much suggested. The other question
is just to give you two modern explanations of this idea of
obligating the man and not obligating the woman. So the most you
know the sort of feminist critique of this would be because we're
talking about it from a patriarchal perspective where the family is defined
as we've talked before you know it's sort of the man's family
and the children are all part of the father's household not part
of the mother's household right I mean these are things we've seen
before in יבמות. Yevamot. And therefore if they're all being born into
the father's household even from different
wives then basically the one who's having the kids is primarily seen
as the father. Right I mean just look in the פסוקים psukim
in the תורה Torah right אברהם הוליד את יצחק Avraham holid et
Yitzchak right אברהם יצחק ויעקב Avraham Yitzchak v'Yaakov right so and so
gave birth you know it's not gave birth the word is הוליד
holid which is the הפעיל hif'il caused to give birth from which
we create an English word of begat or sired but ultimately you
know the woman is the one giving birth but she's invisible אברהם
הוליד את יצחק Avraham holid et Yitzchak where's שרה Sarah you know
but that's sort of the way it's perceived of within a patriarchal
society it's all of the children of the man no matter from
one wife or multiple wives so primarily it is the man who
is having the kids and the woman becomes invisible. Which of course
you know is like obviously one could imagine you know can be
very troubling because here it is the woman who is actually being
pregnant you know having the kids birthing the kids carrying the kids
and so on and yet she's seen as not only you know
as like invisible in the process or not the one that is
מצווה. mitzuveh.
You know and so it's both sort of it's like the worst
of both worlds she's seen societally as having her role to be
the one that's supposed to be at home and get pregnant and
have the kids and then not given credit in terms of sort
of the מצווה mitzvah of having the kids.
Rabbi Saul Berman in a famous article I think the woman's something
status in Judaism or whatever from about 30 years ago tried to
suggest the exact opposite which was to say that by saying that
a woman isn't obligated in פרו ורבו pru u'rvu. what the הלכה
halacha is saying is that she does not have to she's not
forced into the role of child-bearer she can choose to not get
married and not have kids and she can choose a more independent
role and therefore actually is freeing her rather than sort of you
know assigning her the traditional role. So you can decide which one
of those two approaches you prefer or neither of those but anyway
it's quite fascinating yes? This is all pre-Sinai?
Yeah so that's the other thing is that it's basically based on
the פסוקים psukim which gets to גמרא Gemara in סנהדרין Sanhedrin which
is פסוקים psukim that were commanded before מתן תורה Matan Torah and
then weren't repeated. Were they meant for בני נח Bnei Noach or
בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael and so on? So yeah somehow the גמרא
Gemara, is assuming that even though it was pre-סיני Sinai it remains
in effect
but then the funny thing is but only for בני ישראל Bnei
Yisrael or even for בני נח? Bnei Noach? I mean that's all
these discussions in סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. Okay so now the גמרא Gemara. says
like this. אמר רב
יוסף Amar Rav Yosef רב יוסף אמר מהכא Rav Yosef amar mehakha
אני אל שדי פרה ורבה ani El Shaddai pre u'rvu so here
we get a little closer to סיני Sinai although not סיני Sinai
yet אני אל שדי פרה ורבה ani El Shaddai pre u'rvu I
am the Lord God be fruitful and multiply ולא קאמר v'lo kama
פרו ורבו. pru u'rvu Okay so and so that's God speaking to
יעקב Yaakov and it doesn't say פרו ורבו pru u'rvu it says
פרה ורבה pre u'rvu so it's singular.
ואמר רב אילא משום רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון V'amar Rav Ila mishum
Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon of course you could say that he was
already מקיים mikayeim פרו ורבו p'ru u'r'vu, I mean plenty of kids
although maybe he even had דינה Dinah so he already had the
boy and the girl even going to בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. So
alright אמר רב אילא משום רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Amar Rav Ila
mishum Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon so since this since it's the statement
of רב אילא Rav Ila in the name of רבי אלעזר ברבי
שמעון Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon we're going to digress a little and
quote a series of his statements. כשם שמצוה על אדם לומר דבר
הנשמע כך מצוה על אדם שלא לומר דבר שאינו נשמע. Kesheim shemitzvah
al adam lomar davar hanishma kakh mitzvah al adam shelo lomar davar
she’eino nishma. That's really good advice. The same way it's a מצוה
mitzvah to say things that can be heard and not to be
silent when something needs to be said it's a מצוה mitzvah. to
keep your silence when people aren't able to hear. רבי אבא אמר
חובה Rabbi Abba amar chovah it's not only a מצוה mitzvah it's
like you know a real obligation שנאמר אל תוכח לץ פן ישנאך
shene’emar al tokhach leitz pen yisne’eka do not you know remonstrate the
mocker lest he hate you הוכח לחכם ויאהבך. hokhach l'chakham v'ye’ehaveka. Give
תוכחה tokhecha give you know a reproof to the wise person and
he will love you for it. But you're not supposed to tell
people something that they're not able to hear it'll only be counterproductive.
It's only connected because it's רב אילא Rav Ila in the name
of רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון. Another statement of רב אילא in the
name of רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון ואמר רב אילא משום רבי אלעזר
ברבי שמעון מותר לו לאדם לשנות בדבר השלום. V'amar Rav Ila mishum
Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon mutar lo leadam lishnot bidvar hashalom. A person
can alter the truth a little tell a half lie a half
truth for the sake of peace שנאמר אביך צוה shene’emar avikha tziva
right where we're getting up to the פרשה parsha your father commanded.
Father commanded before he died to say forgive, you know, the sin
of יוסף Yosef etcetera. כה תאמרו ליוסף אנא שא נא פשע אחיך
וחטאתם כי רעה גמלוך Ko tomaru l'Yosef anna sa na pesha achecha
v'chatatam ki ra'ah gemalucha etcetera. And then it says, you know, ויבך
יוסף בדברם אליו Vayivk Yosef b'dabram eilav presumably the reason יוסף Yosef
is crying is because he realizes that it's not true, but that
they felt the need to say that obviously meant that they were
still—that they were still terrified of him. So they're—but they're making it
up to try to create peace.
רבי נתן אומר, Rabbi Natan omeir, of course it's interesting, peace is,
you know, basically to protect themselves, you could say it's very self-serving,
but nevertheless, it's to, you know, it's—it's for the sake of peace.
רבי נתן אומר מצוה, Rabbi Natan omeir mitzvah, שנאמר, shene'emar, it's not
just מותר, muttar, it goes—it's a מצוה. mitzvah. It says ויאמר שמואל
איך אלך ושמע שאול Shaul והרגני—שאול will hear and kill me and
then God basically tells him, you know, get—you know, put together this,
like, a wagon and so on and tell him that you're going
to do something else, don't tell him that you're going to anoint
דוד. David. So make up a story. דבי רבי ישמעאל תנא גדול
השלום שאף הקדוש ברוך הוא שינה בו.
Dvei Rabi Yishmael tana: gadol hashalom she'af hakadosh baruch
hu shina bo. Greatest peace that even God altered His words for
the sake of it. דמעיקרא כתיב ואדוני זקן. D'mei-ikara ktiv vadoni zakein.
When שרה Sarah says how can I have a kid and my
master is old, so she says it's אברהם's Avraham fault, which ties
in exactly to the whole question of why is somebody not having
a kid. Right? ובסוף כתיב U'v'sof ktiv and when God says to
אברהם Avraham למה זה צחקה שרה לאמר האף אמנם אלד ואני זקנתי.
Lama zeh tzachaka Sarah leimor ha'af umnam eileid va'ani zakanti. So God
says that שרה Sarah claimed that the problem was with her, whereas
שרה Sarah really claimed the problem was with אברהם, Avraham, exactly the
debate we had before who has the problem. By the way, so
the חתם סופר Chatam Sofer says that it's not speaking about outright
lies, because if you look at the case by שרה, Sarah, שרה
Sarah doesn't just say ואדוני זקן. vadoni zakein. שרה Sarah says—שרה Sarah
says האף אמנם ha'af umnam what does it say?
ותצחק שרה בקרבה לאמר אחרי
בלותי היתה לי עדנה ואדוני זקן.
Vatitzchak Sarah b'kirbah leimor acharei
vloti hayta li ednah vadoni zakein. After I've grown old, how can
I get my youth and my master's old? So she essentially said
both, but God only repeated half of it. Okay? So it's sort
of like the, you know, אנכי עשו בכורך. anochi Eisav bchorecha. Not
exactly, actually here really was half of the story but not the
whole, but at least half of it was accurate. Whether you could
say that about the other cases about אביך צוה, avicha tziva, you
know, which seems to have been made up out of the whole
cloth, you know, maybe you could say well your father would have
commanded had he—you know, had maybe had we told him the whole
story he would have said this. Anyway, it's a question of an
outright lie as opposed to לשנות. l'shanot. לשנות l'shanot is not exactly
the same as לשקר. l'shaker. So maybe there's some difference there. Okay.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this. רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא
אומר, Rabi Yochanan ben Beroka omeir, איתמר. itmar. Okay, so now we
get to רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא Rabi Yochanan ben Beroka who says
reasonably that it's the woman's מצוה mitzvah, as well. איתמר רבי יוחנן
ורבי יהושע בן לוי. Itmar, Rabi Yochanan v'Rabi Yehoshua ben Levi. חד
אמר הלכה כרבי יוחנן בן ברוקא, Chad amar halacha k'Rabi Yochanan ben
Beroka, so there's a debate. רבי יוחנן Rabi Yochanan says we rule
like רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא, Rabi Yochanan ben Beroka, it's the woman's
מצוה. mitzvah וחד אמר אין הלכה כרבי יוחנן בן ברוקא, V'chad amar
ein halacha k'Rabi Yochanan ben Beroka, we don't rule like her.
תסתייים דרבי יוחנן הוא דאמר—now, Tistayayeim d'Rabi Yochanan hu d'amar what's the
difference? Who cares? I mean it's nice to say whether you get
points or not, whether you get credit for the מצוה, mitzvah is
there a bottom line halakhic difference whether if we say the מצוה's
mitzvah on her as well as on him? Can anybody think about
what a possible difference would be?
Can a woman stay single?
Okay, can a woman choose to stay single? Okay. Any other possible
difference is...
What if he has children but she hasn't?
Excellent. Let's say she's already had children with another woman and she
hasn't. Is she allowed to marry this guy if—you know, if he's
no longer able to have kids, or if they're not having kids
can she demand a divorce so she can marry somebody else to
have kids? Right? So it's not just a question of like who
gets credit, there's a lot of practical implications. I'll tell you another
very, other important one, which I mean all of these we're going
to see a variation of in the גמרא, Gemara which is questions
nowadays about, you know, use of birth control. So before one has
fulfilled the מצוה mitzvah of פרו ורבו, p'ru u'r'vu, so if a
woman isn't commanded, so the רב משה Rav Moshe raised the question:
maybe she should go ahead and use the pill, she's not doing
anything wrong, she doesn't have a מצוה mitzvah of פרו ורבו, peru
u-revu, and okay then somehow her husband isn't having kids, but you
know that's not her problem, she's not commanded and she's allowed to
use birth control. So of course then the only way to frame
that question is: is she allowed to do that if it prevents
him from doing his מצוה Mitzvah and this is the only context
in which, you know, she's able to of course have kids? But
it obviously raises interesting questions if she's not commanded, what her freedom
is to choose not to have kids on one hand and if
she is commanded, you know, then what her obligation is or her
right is to demand that she be married to somebody who is
able to give her kids. So let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara Okay. So this is a debate of how do we
rule. תסתייים דרבי יוחנן הוא דאמר אין הלכה. Tistayayeim d'Rabi Yochanan hu
d'amar ein halacha.
Let's conclude that רבי יוחנן Rabi Yochanan is the one who says
we don't rule like רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא Rabi Yochanan ben Beroka
and we say that it's only the man's obligation.
דיתיב רבי אבהו וקאמר משמיה דרבי יוחנן הלכה. D'yativ Rabi Abbahu v'ka'amar
mishmeih d'Rabi Yochanan: halacha.
We rule like רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא, Rabi Yochanan ben Beroka, that
it's the woman's מצוה mitzvah. as well. הדרינהו רבי אמי ורב אסי
לאפייהו. Hadreinh Rabi Ammi v'Rav Assi l'apeihu. הדרינהו רבי אמי ורב אסי
Hadreinh Rabi Ammi v'Rav Assi turned their face away from him, like
they didn't want to outright contradict him, but they showed their displeasure.
So. ואיכא דאמרי V'ika d'amri and some say, רבי חייא בר אבא
אמר, Rabi Chiya bar Abba amar, that it was רבי חייא בר
אבא Rabi Chiya bar Abba who said it. הדרינהו רבי אמי ורב
אסי לאפייהו. Hadreinh Rabi Ammi v'Rav Assi l'apeihu. And it was again
רבי אמי ורב אסי *Rabbi Ami ve'Rav Assi* turned their face away
from him. ואמר רב פפא *ve'amar Rav Pappa*, now רב פפא *Rav
Pappa* says בשלמא *bishlama*, it makes sense that המאן דאמר *hamandamar* רבי
אבהו *Rabbi Abbahu* אמר Amar, *amar* that it was רבי אבהו *Rabbi
Abbahu* said it, משום כבוד בית קיסר *mishum kevod beit Keisar*, because
רבי אבהו *Rabbi Abbahu* was connected to the Caesar's house and therefore
they didn't want to directly contradict him so they just turned their
back to him. ולא אמרו ליה ולא מידי *v'lo amru lei v'lo
midi*, they didn't say anything to him. אלא למאן דאמר *ella l'man
d'amar* רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya, בר אבא *Rabbi Chiya bar Abba* אמר
*amar*, but who is רבי חייא בר אבא *Rabbi Chiya bar Abba*
who said it, so לימרו ליה למה אמר רבי יוחנן הכי *leimru
lei lama amar Rabbi Yochanan hachi*? Let them say explicitly to him,
directly contradict him, so don't just turn your back. Okay, so that
was the question of who said it in the name of רבי
יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*, but either way when it was said over in
the name of רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* that we rule like רבי
יוחנן בן ברוקא *Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka*, they showed their displeasure, they
showed they disagreed. So it seems clear that רבי אמי ורב אסי
*Rabbi Ami ve'Rav Assi* believe that according to רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*
we don't rule like רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא *Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka*,
okay? So that's what the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says, that seems to
be a good reason to assume that רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* says
we don't rule like רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא *Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka*
and we rule that it is only the man's מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah*.
Yes.
Is רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא *Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka* the same as
רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* and ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish*? No, that's exactly
why there's a debate of רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* and רבי יהושע
בן לוי *Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi* who are אמוראים *Amoraim* whether we
rule like רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא *Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka* in the
משנה *Mishnah*. So right now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is saying that
רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*, that when the claim was made that רבי
יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* the אמורא *Amora* ruled like רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא
*Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka* the תנא *Tanna*, רבי אמי ורב אסי *Rabbi
Ami ve'Rav Assi* rejected that. So presumably רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* says
we don't rule like רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא *Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka*
and it's only the man's מצוה mitzvah, *mitzvah*. So the גמרא Gemara,
*Gemara* says מאי הוי עלה *mai havya aleh*? תא שמע דאמר רבי
אחא בר חנינא אמר רבי אבהו אמר רב אסי עובדא הוה קמי
דרבי יוחנן *Ta shema de'amar Rabbi Acha bar Chanina amar Rabbi Abbahu
amar Rav Assi uvda hava kamei d'Rabbi Yochanan*. So now there's a
story that involves רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*, let's take a look. בכנישתא
דקיסרי *bechinishta de'Keisari*, in the synagogue of Caesarea, דאמר יוציא ויתן כתובה
*d'amar yotzi v'yitten ketubah*. And a woman came and basically said, I'm
not able to have kids, you know, this man isn't providing me
kids, you know, maybe and for some reason and he was, she
was suing for divorce and he said he has to divorce her
and give a כתובה *ketubah*. ואי סלקא דעתך לא
מיפקדה *v'isalka daitach lo mifkeda*, so כתובה מאי עבידתא *ketubah mai avidata*?
Presumably the case was that the man already had kids, so it's
not like the earlier case where he has to divorce her in
order to fulfill פרו ורבו peru u-revu, *pru urvu*. He already fulfilled
פרו ורבו peru u-revu? *pru urvu*. She wasn't having kids and she
said maybe it's his fault and I want to get a divorce
and I want to marry somebody else. So he said fine, divorce
her and give the כתובה *ketubah*. But it's saying look,
why is here she entitled to a כתובה *ketubah*? He's saying I
want to stay married, right? You understand the difference. In both cases,
this and the earlier case we had, they weren't having kids. But
the earlier case, we're telling him you're not allowed to stay married,
you have a מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* of פרו ורבו peru u-revu? *pru
urvu*, you have to divorce her. Since it's not necessarily her fault,
you've got to give her the כתובה *ketubah*. Fine, that's when we
were forcing it. This case he's saying I want to stay married,
I've already had kids with another wife, so why should I divorce
her? Why should I pay a כתובה *ketubah*? I'm happy to stay
married and she's suing for divorce. And we said oh she's suing
for divorce, you gotta divorce her and give the כתובה *ketubah*. Why
should I give the כתובה *ketubah*? I want to stay married. So
that's what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, and it says ואי סלקא
דעתך לא מיפקדה *v'isalka daitach lo mifkeda*, if she's not commanded, so
why is she entitled, כתובה מאי עבידתא *ketubah mai avidata*? Why is
she entitled to sue for divorce with a כתובה *ketubah*? Like it's
one thing to say all right be nice to her let her
try to have kids with another guy, but if she doesn't have
a real claim because she doesn't have a real obligation then
why are you forcing a divorce with a כתובה *ketubah*? So the
גמרא *Gemara* says דילמא דבאה מחמת טענה *dilma d'voh machmat tana*? No,
maybe because she has another type of a claim that's not the
technical מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* claim, but it's still a very legitimate claim
why she should be allowed to be divorced so she can try
to have kids with somebody else. What's the example? כי הא דאתא
לקמיה
דרבי אמי *ki ha de'asa l'kamei d'Rabbi Ami*. אמרה ליה Amrah leih,
*amra lei*, she said to him, הבו לי כתובה *hav li ketubah*.
I mean, she said to her husband like, have him divorce me
and give me my כתובה *ketubah*. אמר לה Amar lah, *amar lah*,
he said to her, זיל לא מיפקדת *zil lo mifkadat*. No, go,
you weren't commanded on פרו ורבו pru u'rvu... *pru urvu*, so even
if the guy divorces you, ultimately it's not with cause, it's a
divorce without cause because you have no claim that you have a
right to have kids. If it's a divorce with cause you're entitled
to your כתובה *ketubah*, but if it's not with cause you're not,
and since you're not commanded there's no cause. אמרה ליה Amrah leih,
*amra lei*, she said back to him, לשיבותא דלה מאי תיהוי עלה
*l'siva d'la mai tehvei alah*? But in my old age, or literally
her old age, what's going to happen to her?
Meaning it's very nice I'm not commanded, but I still want to
have kids, I want people's kids to take care of me when
I get old, you know, right now we'd just
say my basic human need and desire to have
kids and as a woman I want to be a mother and
so on, so forget a מצוה mitzvah. *mitzvah*, as a human being
I'm entitled to have kids, who's going to take care of me
when I get old? So
אמר *amar*, he said, הכי ודאי כפינן *hi vadai kafinan*. Oh, in
that case then of course we'll force a divorce and make you
pay the כתובה *ketubah*. That's a real, that's real with cause. So
it's quite interesting, right? No need to have a מצוה. The point
is, if somebody can sue for divorce with cause, the woman, then
she, you know, if it's not seen as to be not with
legitimate cause, maybe fine, give the גט, but she loses her כתובה.
If it's legitimate cause, you gotta pay the כתובה. So the גמרא
is saying that even without the מצוה פרו ורבו, pru u'rvu it's
a very legitimate human desire to say I want to have the
opportunity to actually have kids.
And this brings in an economic issue.
Oh, you think of who's going to take care of me? Absolutely.
Yeah, but that's not normally the way the כתובה issues work. I
mean, when we get to כתובות, Ketubot, we'll see like a whole
wide range of like legitimate cause, not legitimate cause, like fault divorce
and no-fault divorce, you know, and it's not seen as like the
כתובה is to pay for the cost or something. It just means
is the person entitled to be suing for divorce or not? But
it's interesting, you know, I hadn't thought about that point. Okay. So
it says like this: ההיא דאתאי לקמיה דרב נחמן, Hahi de-atai l-kamieh
d-Rav Nachman, a woman came in front of רב נחמן. Rav Nachman.
אמר לה, he said to her, לא מפקדת, lo mifkadt, you're not
commanded, so you can't demand a כתובה even if you get divorced.
אמרה ליה, לא בעיא הך איתתא חוטרא לידה ומרא לקבורה, lo ba'ya
hach iteta chutra l-yadah u-mara l-kvurah, doesn't this woman, isn't this woman,
doesn't this woman need a staff for her hand and a shovel
for her grave? So somebody can support me in my old age
and bury me when I die. אמר, כי הא ודאי כפינן. ki
ha vadai kafinan. Oh, in that case, we will sue for divorce.
So this is why, you know, people need lawyers, because somebody needs
to tell somebody this is the claim. Everybody can make this claim,
right? Which is pretty funny. Why do you wait for the woman
to make the claim? I mean, that's also pretty funny, right? It
shows you something about the society in which that if a woman
didn't make this claim, you wouldn't assume that this is like, you
know, a basic issue that everybody's, you know, you know, is entitled
to. Okay. So the upshot of all this seems to be that
a woman is not commanded on פרו ורבו, pru u'rvu, but she
can still sue for divorce if she's not having kids. Okay. יהודה
וחזקיה תאומי הוו, Yehudah v-Chizkiyah te'omei havu,
יהודה Yehudah and חזקיה Chizkiyah were twins.
אחת נגמרה צורתו לסוף תשעה ואחת נגמרה צורתו לסוף שבעה. Achat nigmerah
tzuratoh l-sof tish'ah v-achat nigmerah tzuratoh l-sof shiv'ah. Okay, one of them
sort of was finished being formed after nine months, one after seven
months. Not going to get into that now. יהודית דביתהו דרבי חייא.
Yehudit dveitehu d-Rabbi Chiya. Anyway, the point was that it caused
their mother יהודית, Yehudit, who was דביתהו דרבי חייא, dveitehu d-Rabbi Chiya,
the wife of רבי חייא, who was the one who had these
kids, יהודה Yehudah and חזקיה, Chizkiyah, it's like another,
you know, whatever, רבקה Rivkah with יעקב Yaakov and עשו, Esav, you
had these two kids that are forming in her womb at different
times. She's obviously not going to be an easy pregnancy. So הוי
לה צערא דלידה, hava lah tza'ara d-leidah, she had a very difficult
time having births with them. שינתה
מנה, Shinatah manah, so she changed her clothes, she disguised herself, ואתאי
לקמיה דרבי חייא, v-atai l-kamieh d-Rabbi Chiya, she came to her husband
to ask for פסק, psak, but she was dressed up as a
different woman.
So he didn't know she was.
If she had had a telephone, it would have made it a
lot easier. אמרה ליה, she said, איתתא מפקדא אפרייה ורבייה, iteta mifkeda
a-pirya v-rivya, Rabbi, is a woman commanded on פרו ורבו? pru u'rvu.
אמר לה, לא. She said no.
אזלה אשתיא סמא דעקרתא, Azlah ashtaya sama d-akrta, so she went and
she drank
some potion, some, you know, some medicine that made her sterile, some
sterilizing potion, cause she didn't want to have any more kids and
מרן Maran told me I wasn't
commanded. ולסוף איגלי מילתא, U-l-sof igli milta, in the
end the matter was revealed. Somehow he realized what she had done,
why weren't they having any more kids, I don't know, or he
found the, you know, he found the mixtures of the potion in
the house, the vial or something, I don't know. אמר לה, he
said to her, איכו ילדת לי חדא כרסא אחריתי, eichu yaladt li
chada karsa achriti, I wish you would have just waited to have
had that we would have had one more pair of kids. Nice
for him to say. דאמר מר, d-amar mar, now apparently he was
already יוצא פרו ורבו yotzei peru u-revu because we've taught, יהודה וחזקיה
אחי, Yehudah v-Chizkiyah achi, יהודה Yehudah and חזקיה Chizkiyah were brothers, they
were twins, they were his children, and also פזי וטבי אחוותא, Pazi
v-Tavi achvata, פזי Pazi and טבי Tavi were sisters, and apparently were
also twins. And all these were his kids, so he was already
יוצא פרו ורבו yotzei peru u-revu twice, two boys and two girls.
But he said I wish you just would have waited to one
more crop of kids, one more pair of kids before you would
have done this. But otherwise he wasn't so upset. So is this
evidence that a woman is able to go ahead and use birth
control if she's not commanded and let the chips fall where they
may? Well, the difference is that in this story the man was
already יוצא פרו ורבו, yotzei peru u-revu, right? So whether she's able
to do this, you know, in other cases also raises the question
why she asked as a woman commanded in פרו ורבו? Even if
a woman is commanded, if she had had two boys and two
girls, she was already יוצא, yotzei, unless the two girls were from
some other
woman. So it's a little funny exactly the story, right? You'd have
to, but and what sort of הלכה halachic implications you can learn
from it. But nevertheless, what you do see is that in some
cases if the woman is not commanded, she has more latitude in
terms of choosing to actually, you know, use birth control and not
have kids.
Right. פזי Pazi means Goldie. What's טבי? Tavi?
I don't know. Okay. So the גמרא says it just ends, ואמר
רב אחא בר קטינא אמר רבי יצחק מעשה באשה אחת שחציה שפחה
וחציה בת חורין וכפו את רבה ועשאה בת חורין, v-amar Rav Acha
bar Katina amar Rabbi Yitzchak ma'aseh b-ishah achat she-chatziyah shifchah v-chatziyah bat
chorin v-kafu et rabah v-asa'ah bat chorin, a woman who was half
slave half free that they forced the master to free her, we've
had cases like that about a man who is half slave half
free, and presumably the reason is to entitle her to have kids
because when you're in that state of half slave half free you
can't get married to a free man or to a slave. or
to a slave. So presumably we would not force the master to
free her unless she was obligated to have kids. So the גמרא
says: No, אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak
מנהג הפקר נהגו בה, minhag hefker nahagu bah, that was not because
she was obligated to have kids, that was because people were taking
sexual advantage of her. And if she couldn't be married to either
free men or a slave, there was nobody, she was going to
be
basically used, taken advantage of
by sexual advantage of and therefore they had to do something about
it. But you can't prove from that that a woman has a
מצוה. So all of the dominant end of the בבלי Bavli is
almost consistently that the מצוה is not on the woman. You should
be aware that there is a ירושלמי Yerushalmi makes it sound like
it's, from what I remember at least, that it's more open debate
or that the מצוה, that we might actually פוסק pasken that the
מצוה is on the woman. And two final comments to make about
this, one is the issue
about what do you call it? About the challenge of a woman
giving birth. The משך חכמה Meshech Chochma uses this to explain why
a woman is exempt, going back to that question. People, the following
reason I'm about to say, people think this is like מסיני, mi'Sinai,
but as far as I can understand to detect it was only
the משך חכמה Meshech Chochma was the first to say it about
150 years ago and he said because since childbirth creates a certain
amount of risk, it entails a certain amount of risk to the
woman, the תורה Torah can't mandate it for the woman and therefore
it has to make it more of a free choice of the
woman. And that's why the woman is not commanded. So that's his
explanation and a lot of people sort of like that explanation, whether
it's the true explanation
or not, but that is an explanation that for a lot of
people resonate.
I don't see a hint of that in the גמרא, but anyway
that's one way of dealing with this challenge that the woman is
one having the kids but not the one commanded, dealing with the
risks of childbirth. The other interesting thing that's worth noting is,
and now it just flew out of my head.
One minute. Woman
is commanded פרו ורבו...
oh
yes. So we say whether the woman is commanded or not in
פרו ורבו and the גמרא seems to conclude that a woman is
not. There's an interesting position of תוספות Tosafot which also people somehow
accept as like
הלכה למעשה, halacha l'maaseh, but it's not even brought down in שולחן
ערוך, Shulchan Aruch, it's one opinion in one
תוספות, Tosafot, which is that a woman has some idea called of
this broader concept of לשבת. lashevet. Remember we quoted the פסוק pasuk
before לא תהו בראה לשבת יצרה, lo tohu b'ra'ah lashevet yetzarah, settling
the world and so on. So there's one opinion in תוספות Tosafot
that even though a woman is not commanded in פרו ורבו, she's
part of this broader mandate of לשבת. lashevet. And what that means
is it might not translate into exactly one boy and one girl
or a strict obligation, but it doesn't mean that she's completely excluded
from it. It's more sort of like she's mandated by the value
of the מצוה if not by the technical form of the מצוה.
So it's worth noting that that is a position of תוספות Tosafot
and it's a serious question whether it really is a position of
פסק הלכה psak halacha or not, but it's something that gets discussed
a lot. Okay, and with that we end this פרק, perek, הדרן
עלך הבא יבמתו, hadran alach HaBa Yevimto, and that discussion of פרו
ורבו. Let's get started now on the next פרק perek and on
what officially is today's דף, maybe get halfway caught up. אלמנה לכהן
גדול, Almana l'Kohen Gadol, גרושה וחלוצה לכהן הדיוט. grusha v'chalutza l'Kohen Hedyot.
Once again back to כהנים. Kohanim. So an אלמנה almana married to
a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol or גרושה וחלוצה grusha v'chalutza to a
כהן הדיוט, Kohen Hedyot, כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, these are cases obviously
where it's a forbidden marriage, but it's binding. The child isn't a
ממזר, mamzer, but the woman, and we know as a result becomes
a חללה chalala because of this forbidden act of sex with a
כהן. Kohen. הכניסה לו עבדי מלוג ועבדי צאן ברזל. hechnisa lo avdei
melog v'avdei tzon barzel.
She brings into the marriage slaves which are part of her נכסי
מלוג nichsei melog or slaves which are part of her נכסי צאן
ברזל. nichsei tzon barzel. נכסי צאן ברזל Nichsei tzon barzel literally means
iron sheep. I don't know what the word מלוג melog meant, I'm
sure it comes from some Greek word or something, I have no
idea. Anyway, what's the difference? The difference is the following. נכסי
צאן ברזל Nichsei tzon barzel because a property she brings into the
marriage
that basically title transfers to the husband. So she brings in some
real estate, you basically write over the deed to the husband, he
is now the owner of that property. The only thing is
you assess the value of that property and if they get divorced
or if he dies before her, she takes that value back out
of the marriage. But he now completely has the title, but he
has an outstanding debt for the value, he owes her for the
full value of that property. That's by the way in the כתובה
when we write,
when we say that the property she brings
in, בין במאני דלבושא בין במאני דארסא הכל קיבל עליו חתן דנן
במאה זקוקים כסף צרוף. bein b'manei d'levusha bein b'manei d'arsa hakol kibel
alav chatan denan b'meah zekukim kesef tzaruf. What that means is she's
bringing in all of this dowry, the title is transferring totally to
him and we're assessing its value at a hundred זקוק zekuk of
silver, as like ten thousand dollars. And that means if they get
divorced or he dies before her she takes ten thousand dollars out
of the marriage.
That's
נכסי צאן ברזל. nichsei tzon barzel.
So he does get the, so that's an interesting question, so yes,
I mean the question is that like let's say the property is
still בעין, be'ayin, but it's worth less and so on, but let's
for now just not worry about that, just say she gets the
value of it back out of the marriage.
Okay. נכסי מלוג nichsei milug is easier or I don't know easier,
נכסי מלוג nichsei milug is she retains title, but he has the
right to benefit from it during the marriage, called the usufruct, right,
the קנין פירות, kinyan peiros, the right of the fruits, right to
benefit from it. So it's still her plot of land, but any
earnings off of that land, any rental, you know, income, any crops,
any harvest, whatever, all of that goes to him during the marriage,
but she retains the title. So now let's say we're talking not
about land but about slaves. So she brings slaves in, if they're
נכסי צאן ברזל, nichsei tzon barzel, they totally transfer to him. So
her status about whether the slaves can eat תרומה, terumah, the whole
question here is the slaves of a כהן kohen eat תרומה. terumah.
Okay. So נכסי צאן ברזל, nichsei tzon barzel, they're totally his slaves.
So even if she, it's a forbidden marriage and she's a חללה
chalalah and whatever it is, it's his slaves, they eat תרומה. terumah.
But נכסי מלוג, nichsei milug, they're her slaves. Okay. So can the
slaves of the wife of a כהן kohen eat תרומה? terumah? I
don't mean the slaves of a כהן, kohen, it's a כהן's kohen's
wife can eat תרומה terumah and the slaves of a כהן kohen
can eat תרומה, terumah, what about the slaves of a כהן's kohen's
wife? And the general answer is yes, except here there's a little
bit of a problem because it's a forbidden marriage, she's a חללה.
chalalah. So if they're eating תרומה terumah by virtue of her, not
by virtue of him, then and she's a חללה chalalah and she's
disqualified from תרומה, terumah, right, if he was married to a ישראלית
Yisraelis or he was married to a בת כהן, bas kohen, they
eat תרומה terumah because they're his wife. But if he's married to
a woman he's forbidden to be married to, a גרושה אלמנה, gerusha
almanah, he can't eat, she's a חללה, chalalah, she's not allowed to
eat תרומה. terumah. So can her slaves eat תרומה? terumah? Okay.
Correct. That is all, that is the case. A כהן kohen never
becomes invalid, it's only the woman that through this forbidden act of
sex becomes invalidated, okay, and the children. So here he's a כהן,
kohen, if he, here he's married to, I don't know, let's just
say ישראלית, Yisraelis, okay, so she brings two things into the marriage.
So the עבדי צאן ברזל, avdei tzon barzel,
okay, these both came from her, okay. Oops, I wrote with a
ג. gimmel. That came from her but right now they're his. So
they eat תרומה terumah by virtue of, by virtue of him, okay.
And the עבדי מלוג avdei milug are hers, okay. They both came
from her. All right, but that's, so that's a normal situation. And
she eats תרומה. terumah. So does she eat תרומה? terumah? She eats
תרומה terumah because she's אשת כהן, eishes kohen, okay, so she eats
תרומה. terumah. These eat תרומה terumah because they're עבדי כהן, avdei kohen,
okay. And these guys here eat תרומה terumah in this normal case
because they're עבדים avadim of the אשת כהן, eishes kohen, of אשת
כהן. eishes kohen. That's in a normal case, okay. But if she's
a חללה, chalalah, right, if she's a חללה, chalalah, then she doesn't
eat תרומה, terumah, these guys eat תרומה, terumah, and these guys eat
תרומה? terumah? So presumably no, because since they're eating תרומה terumah comes
via her. Okay. So that's the issue. So let's take a look.
So Melog comes from the word property that the wife brings, property
that the
wife brings.
Exactly what he is. Okay fine. All right. Okay, so ועבדי מלוג
לא יאכלו בתרומה ועבדי צאן ברזל יאכלו בתרומה. v'avdei milug lo yochlu
b'terumah v'avdei tzon barzel yochlu b'terumah.
Okay.
So that's exactly that difference. ואלו הם עבדי מלוג, v'elu hem avdei
milug, these are the servants of מלוג, milug, אם מתו מתו לה,
im meisu meisu lah, if they die it's her loss, because she's
the one that still has title, ואם הותירו הותירו לה, v'im hosiru
hosiru lah, and if they increase in value it's her gain. אף
על פי שהוא חייב במזונותן, af al pi shehu chayav bimzonosan, now
he has to feed them, right, because remember, he has rights to
the עבדי מלוג, avdei milug, he gets their work, he has benefits
from them, and he has a responsibility to make sure that they're
fed. Nevertheless, even though he feeds them and he gets their benefits,
they're her property. Okay. הרי אלו לא יאכלו בתרומה. harei elu lo
yochlu b'terumah.
So even so, they're her property and therefore they do not eat
in תרומה. terumah. ואלו הן עבדי צאן ברזל, v'elu hen avdei tzon
barzel, these are עבדי צאן ברזל, avdei tzon barzel, אם מתו מתו
לו, im meisu meisu lo, if they, she has title, if they
die it's his loss, ואם הותירו הותירו לו, v'im hosiru hosiru lo,
if they increase, have kids I guess or increase in value, it's
his gain. הואיל והוא חייב באחריותן, ho'il v'hu chayav beachrayusan, הרי אלו
יאכלו בתרומה. harei elu yochlu b'terumah.
Since he is the one that's responsible for them, meaning he's the
one that gains or loses, they're essentially his, then they eat תרומה
terumah because they're because, they're eating by virtue of him. בת ישראל
שנישאת לכהן והכניסה לו עבדים. bas Yisrael shenises l'kohen v'hichnisah lo avadim.
Now if you have a normal בת ישראל, bas Yisrael, not a
woman who's going to become a חללה, chalalah, like... just marries a
non-כהן Kohein woman, בין עבדי מלוג בין עבדי צאן ברזל יאכלו בתרומה,
bein avdei milug bein avdei tzon barzel yochlu bitrumah, the standard case
they can eat בתרומה bitrumah because they're through her because she's allowed
to eat תרומה Trumah so they can eat תרומה Trumah as well.
ובת כהן שניסת לישראל, Uvas Kohein shenises leYisrael,
now a כהן Kohein woman who's married to a ישראל, Yisrael,
now once she marries a ישראל Yisrael she's no longer allowed to
eat תרומה, Trumah, right? והכניסה לו עבדים בין עבדי מלוג בין עבדי
צאן ברזל לא יאכלו בתרומה, vehichnisa lo avadim bein avdei milug bein
avdei tzon barzel lo yochlu bitrumah, so in that case obviously they
can't because they can't eat by virtue of him and they can't
eat by virtue of her. Very easy.
עבדים כנעני, avadim kenaani, property, right? Property.
Okay,
so let's look a little bit at the גמרא, ואבדי מלוג לא
יאכלו בתרומה אמאי, veavdei milug lo yochlu bitrumah amai, why do they
not eat תרומה? Trumah? להוי כקנינו שקנה קנין, lahavei kekinyano shekana kinyan,
let this be like his acquisition, now we're going to have to
refer to his wife as an acquisition, so let it be like
his acquisition that owns an acquisition and let them somehow eat indirectly
through him, ignore the fact that she's a חללה chalalah and sort
of see this as an indirect acquisition of his own. The obvious
answer is that we won't see it that way and we're also
going to bracket or whatever note the fact that the wife is
being referred to as a קנין. kinyan. דתניא מנין לכהן שנשא אשה
וקנה עבדים שיאכלו בתרומה, detanya minayin leKohein shenasa isha vekana avadim sheyochlu
bitrumah,
how do you know in a normal case that a כהן's Kohein
wife or slaves can eat תרומה? Trumah? שנאמר וכהן כי יקנה נפש
קנין כספו הוא יאכל בו, shene'emar veKohein ki yikneh nefesh kinyan kaspo
hu yochal bo,
when he acquires a soul they will eat the תרומה, Trumah, so
acquiring the soul is either slaves or a wife who's acquired through
כסף, kessef, if a wife is considered קנין כספו, kinyan kaspo, something
we will deal plenty with when we deal with קידושין. Kiddushin. ומנין
לאשה שקנתה עבדים, uminayin le'isha shekansah avadim,
how do you know if the wife owns slaves? או עבדיו שקנו
עבדים, o avadav shekanu avadim, or his slaves own slaves, right? That's
fascinating, a slave can own a slave, but if you give a
slave property on the condition that the master does not have ownership
over it, he can own property independent of the master. How do
you know in those cases שיאכלו בתרומה? sheyochlu bitrumah? שנאמר וכהן כי
יקנה נפש קנין כספו הוא יאכל בו. shene'emar veKohein ki yikneh nefesh
kinyan kaspo hu yochal bo.
So the way we're reading this is קנינו שקנה קנין, kinyano shekana
kinyan, it's a כהן כי יקנה קנין כספו
נפש,
Kohein ki yikneh
kinyan kaspo nefesh,
if the thing he has purchased acquires a soul, then also it
will eat in the תרומה, Trumah, אוכל, ochel, so קנינו שקנה קנין
אוכל. kinyano shekana kinyan ochel.
So why is it here the עבדי מלוג avdei milug are owned
indirectly through the כהן, Kohein, his קנין, kinyan, his wife as it
were, owns the עבדים, avadim, so let them eat? So the גמרא
says what I've already told you: no. כל האוכל מאכיל כל שאינו
אוכל אינו מאכיל. kol ha'ochel ma'achil kol she'eino ochel eino ma'achil.
Anybody who can eat, if the woman's entitled to eat, she can
have her slaves eat; they're eating by virtue of her, through her.
If the slave can eat, then the slave's slaves can eat, but
if the woman can't eat because she became a חללה, chalalah, then
the slaves cannot eat through her by virtue of her because she
herself cannot eat.
ולאו, velo, is that really true? דהרי ערל וכל
הטמאים, deharei areil vechol hatmei'im, how about a כהן Kohein is an
ערל areil or כהן Kohein is טמא tamei שאין אוכלים, she'ein ochlim,
they're not allowed to eat תרומה, Trumah, ומאכילים, umachilin, their slaves can
eat or their wives can eat. התם פומייהו כאיב
להו, hasam pumayu ka'iv lehu, there their mouth is hurting them and
that's why they can't eat, which means that that's not seen as
a permanent status. An ערל areil in theory, even though for medical
reasons it's not possible, but in theory could always become a non-ערל.
areil. A טמא tamei could become טהור. tahor. So if it's a
temporary status, then their wives and slaves and others can eat by
virtue of them. But something like a חללה, chalalah, that's a permanent
status and therefore nobody can eat by virtue of her. Let's do
one more line. והרי ממזר שאין אוכל ומאכיל, veharei mamzer she'ein ochel
umachil,
how about a ממזר? mamzer, Now it doesn't really mean a
ממזר, mamzer, it does mean a ממזר, but it's not limited to
a ממזר, it's basically a case about
a grand—let's stop here, I can't spend too much time explaining this.
Okay, so we will pick up with this tomorrow.
Yes, how did this come up earlier? But what about if she's
an אלמנה almanah and he marries her before he becomes כהן גדול?
Kohein Gadol?
Yes, that did come up earlier.